this program is brought to you by
stanford university
we're discussing
just
to fill in a to fill in a point which is
an interesting point
the
behavior of a light ray either in a
gravitational field or in an
accelerating elevator
not when the light ray is traveling
across the elevator but when the light
ray is traveling vertical in the
elevator how do we understand or what
what should we deduce
from einstein's principle of equivalence
what should we deduce about a light ray
which is beamed vertically upward for
example
and which is then detected
up on the roof of the building
somewheres
all right
what does anything interesting happen to
that light now of course if light was
just an ordinary particle a bullet shot
upward you know what the effect of
gravity on the uh
on the bullet is
it
decelerates the bullet
bullet going upward gravity pulling it
downward slows the motion and
effectively removes kinetic energy from
the bullet so the person on the ceiling
sees a slower bullet than the bullet
that we fire it upward
things are a little more involved when
we take into account relativity
and in particular when we take into
account the relativity which has to do
with things moving very close to the
speed of light no we're talking now
about light things moving with the speed
of light
everybody sees the same speed of light
but something happens to a light beam
that's fired upward
namely its color changes or its
frequency changes
and the effect is very easy to
understand in the in the elevator not so
easy to understand if you're thinking
about gravity and you're thinking about
god knows what is the effect of gravity
on a vertical light beam
don't ask that question says einstein
ask what's the effect of a light beam
let's say shot vertically upward from
the floor when it's detected at the
ceiling or vice versa i think i'll go
the other way let's take the light beam
shot
downward
from the uh from the roof of the
elevator
and let's suppose that it has a certain
frequency
right
what happens by the time the light ray
hits the bottom
by the time the light ray hits the
bottom
in fact let's imagine starting
with the elevator at rest it doesn't
matter whether the elevator is at rest
but let's imagine starting at this time
when the elevator is at rest with
respect to us sitting here
all right by the time the light ray gets
down here the elevator is now moving
upward but it's also got a it's not just
it isn't just displaced upward it's
moving upward with a velocity
in other words what's seen down here is
exactly what would be seen if a light
ray was sent downward but then
intercepted by something with a vertical
component of velocity
well
you know what happens to a light beam
when it's intercepted by something
moving relative to the source it's
doppler shifted
just good old doppler shift so you can
estimate pretty accurately rather
accurately to say yes
but wouldn't those doppler shifts cancel
no because the source is moving no no no
no no no no when when they when the beam
was fired the sauce was at rest
but the elevator is accelerating upward
so by the time the beam gets here the
lra the elevator is moving upward right
velocity oh constant velocity of the
castle that's exactly right with
constant absolutely right with constant
velocity the two doppler shifts the
doppler shift would cancel
right
uh it's the accelerated effect
which makes the detector be moving
faster upward than the uh than the
than the emitter
so it's a little exercise you can do the
exercise
just say
now there's a bit of an approximation
here because you really should use the
full general relativity or the full at
least special relativity in doing this
but you can get very close to the right
answer
just by saying how long does it take the
light rate to go from here to here well
it moves with the speed of light the
height of the elevator is h let's call
it and you know as well as i do how to
compute the amount of time that it takes
for the for the
light beam to reach the bottom
but then you can estimate
if you know how much time and it's been
accelerating with a uniform acceleration
you can compute the upward velocity when
the light beam hits the floor and then
just apply the standard doppler shift
formula go look it up on the internet
doppler shift formula and you can detect
and you can determine
the change in frequency
during the fall of the right light ray
down to the floor
that's exactly the same effect that
happens uh to a light ray
near the surface of the earth
when it's fired downward
this has been tested in a big high tower
laser beam downward
detector laser beam at the roof
downwards detector at the bottom the
color of the light ray is a little bit
bluer
than it would have been
if it would have been detected up at the
top of its arc okay
and uh precisely the same effect but
precisely the opposite effect of course
would happen if you fired the light beam
from the floor
and detected it at the ceiling
then you would see a bit of redshift
exactly the opposite thing and in fact
this is of course true when a light beam
departs
from
the surface of the sun or anything like
that
it's detected
a little bit redshifted far away
so for example the spectral lines
of various atomic transitions and things
like that
when they would be measured on the earth
by a telescope would be slightly shifted
from the values you would expect because
they were shifted by exactly this effect
it's a small effect
for the sun
all right so i just thought i would
explain
that phenomenon
wouldn't it be a large effect or a very
large star
it is a large effect
the relevant issue actually is the
escape velocity
so if it's a large star but it's spread
out all over the place over a very very
large diameter
then the effect is not so big if it's
squashed then the effect is big and in
fact the effect is enormous from the
surface of a black hole
from the surface of a black hole the
effect is huge
and
you know the bluest light
would appear
if emitted somewheres near the surface
of a black hole
would appear
deeply infrared
by the time it got out
okay but we'll that's that's another
story that we'll come to
but generally speaking i think the
answer would be yes it would be a bigger
effect for a large star
oh excuse me
very good
you're welcome
remind me remind me the bag is here oh
oh rick will you remind me the bag is
here there's something in it for you
yeah i'll give it to you now
this is for the nice dinner that you
served me just in case you didn't bring
me i knew you wouldn't bring me a cookie
so
no no
there's something that was just in case
my friend didn't bring me a cookie today
yeah
so the light shift the red blue
doesn't that go against the equivalence
principle because if you're it is the
equivalence principle it says gravity is
equivalent to a field of acceleration
okay now i think about the idea that you
know accelerated frame of reference
if everything's moving with you you
wouldn't know that you're really no
that's not true if you're in well if
you're an accelerated frame of reference
you you can tell either that you're
accelerated or that you're in a
gravitational field you can tell that
you're not in free fall
in free fall
if the elevator was freely falling okay
so here's another issue if the elevator
is freely falling let's suppose the
elevator is freely falling in a
gravitational field and we do the same
experiment
we
shoot the light ray down now we are in a
real gravitational field
the effect of the real gravitational
field is to ridden the light
but
the acceleration of the elevator gives
rise to a little bit of doppler shift as
it's moving down and they exactly cancel
each other so that in free fall
the elevator experiment would not detect
the shift of light that's another
example of the equivalence principle
that gravity can be cancelled so to
speak by a field of acceleration
up to up to a point up to a point that
will
well when the light was emitted
it's moving slower than when it's no
it's moving with the speed of light
yeah but what i'm saying is that the
floor is moving faster
later on
than when the light was emitted so it
would still be stretched
it would be redshifted it's written uh
it's freefall no no but that's canceled
by the genuine blue shift due to the
genuine gravitational field here yeah
but it's it but it was blue shifted by a
different amount than it was
exactly
no the blue shift
the shift
in the freely falling elevator there is
no shift they cancel but it's but it's
accelerating it's not in constant
velocity it's freely falling
it's freely falling okay it is
accelerated it's accelerated just like a
real elevator would accelerate it's
accelerating downward
two things are going on
one is the light beam as seen from the
outside
as seen from outside the elevator
if the detector was standing still if
the detector was standing still the
light beam would be blue shifted
but now because by the time the light
ray gets there the elevator bottom is
moving downward
there is a cancelling effect of a
doppler shift now to prove that those
cancel each other you have to do a
little calculation
well i i agree that there's going to be
the cancellation effect but there will
be a slight difference because of the
difference in the velocity at the time
of detection and the time of the
emission but that can't be
because if that were so einstein's
equivalence principle would simply be
wrong
what einstein's equivalence principle
says
is that you get a complete cancellation
apart from tidal forces apart from the
fact
that gravity varies in strength over the
size of the elevator apart from that
fact
it says that a freely falling elevator
in a gravitational field is exactly the
same as an elevator in free space
not accelerated with no gravitational
field
all right so i invite you to make a
little calculation it's just a little
bit of application of doppler shift if
you're the formula for doppler shift is
easy
and i'm not going to do it on the
blackboard now
and of course
if you really want to do it exactly you
have to do it with a special theory of
relativity you can't do it with just uh
it's true
that if you do it just using um
non-relativistic formulas you're going
to get a little bit of shift which is
going to be second order and velocity
divided by the speed of light
uh
using special relativity you'll find
that they exactly cancel
okay that's and that's important that's
an important fact okay
uh let's just let me just remind you
in reference to this again
that
an accelerated reference frame
can be thought of one in which the
coordinate chart let's think of a
coordinate chart
coordinates distance we imagine the
acceleration going off to the right we
prefer
we imagined our elevator moving off to
the right with some acceleration
and then i
explained
that
the coordinate frame within the elevator
the meter sticks let's see if we have
another pin here
the meter sticks
which are
standing at rest
in the elevator
having in the accelerated elevator when
viewed from the rest frame
of course have a curved trajectory that
curved trajectory is the consequence of
the acceleration
in fact if we imagined that the elevator
was accelerating forever accelerating to
the right forever what that really means
is that it came in from the left it
decelerated and then when it went off to
the right
uniform acceleration
that means long in the past it was
coming in it slowed down and it uh and
it accelerated off to the right
then
the trajectories of the endpoints
of the meter stick would be parabolas it
would look something like that
the main lesson here is
oh and of course the rest frame
the meter sticks just just stay at rest
whoops i didn't draw that very well but
you get the point
the interesting thing is
the correspondence between gravity
and the use of cur of a curved
coordinate system
we start
perhaps in absolutely free space
and we use an inertial reference frame
an inertial reference frame is just a
frame at rest in which the meter sticks
are standing still in other words it's
the frame
uh defined by these vertical
y axes or time axes so to speak
but then we look at it from within the
elevator
and from within the elevator the the
trajectories are from outside excuse me
from outside the elevator the meter
sticks of the elevator are curved
trajectories and so we outside the
elevator will
blame
the peculiar things that the person
inside the elevator sees what are those
peculiar things called
gravity
the peculiar phenomena of gravity we
will blame it
on the use of these curved coordinates
we will say sure if we describe nature
in terms of curved coordinates we're
going to see some funny things
the
lesson is
that you can remove the effects of
gravity
by going from one coordinate system to
another but to do so you have to
introduce various kinds of curvature
into the coordinates
the curvature is just another way of
speaking about acceleration
so
does the elevator have gravity in it or
doesn't the elevator have gravity in it
one analysis
says it has gravity in it the other
analysis from another coordinate frame
removes the gravity and blames it on
acceleration
now what about real gravity due to a
planet or a star or something like that
that's more complicated as i mentioned
last time or time before that
you could try to remove the effects of
gravity by going to a freely falling
vertical elevator
and indeed that would remove most of the
effects of the gravity of the earth for
example in a freely falling elevator but
there would be some leftover little bits
the leftover little bits of effect
and those leftover little bits would be
the tidal forces
which are due to the fact that there's a
variation in the strength of gravity
that gravity is stronger near the bottom
than it is near the top and in fact if
you looked at the overall situation
where you might introduce a lot of
elevators
there's obviously no way
that any single
choice of accelerated reference frame
can remove the whole effect of gravity
the whole effect of gravity
at best you could remove it within a
small volume over which gravity doesn't
change very much
over a relatively short time which it
doesn't change very much
that you can do you can remove the
effects of gravity
uh
in a freeling falling elevator for a
short time and a short distance but you
can't remove it globally
there's an obstruction the obstruction
is the gravity the the
the non-uniformity
of the gravitational field which is
caused by the mass
so mass presents an obstruction
to getting rid of gravitational field by
coordinate transformation yeah
when
when you use riddler coordinates are you
ignoring the title
forces
uh no
well first of all i'm not using the
coordinates because i'm not doing
special relativity we're doing
no no
okay i know what you're asking and that
it's
it's more than i want to answer right
now let's not uh let's not get into
rindler rindler
yeah okay um we're still in the
approximation where we're not really
thinking about
relativity we're just thinking more or
less newtonian plus equivalence
principle
all right so you can't really remove a
gravitational field
by choosing accelerated coordinate
systems
tidal forces can't be removed the fact
that you have to accelerate in different
directions at different places doesn't
really make sense
as i said there is an obstruction to
getting rid of the gravitational field
by coordinate transformation
that obstruction is closely related
to the obstruction
in
removing the curvature of a curved space
and that's what i want to come to now i
want to come to the differential
geometry and the mathematics
of curved spaces that's going to take us
some time we're not going to be able to
do it all in one lecture
i'm not sure how many lectures
the basic tool is no more really no more
complicated
than the calculus multi-variable
calculus
i have to assume that you're familiar
with some multi-variable calculus
i'm not going to teach it here but
really just partial derivatives and a
little bit more than that is really all
we need to get a start on the basic
ideas of what curved space is a curved
space and space-time
we're not going to start with space-time
we're just going to think about space
and later on we'll generalize things to
space-time
all right but before we start
just a very very quick review
of one or two very small things about
multi-variable calculus we'll use them
over and over again
supposing we have
some space which we can draw is two
dimensional
we can put some coordinates on it
right we can put some coordinates on it
in this case it's just a two dimensional
space the space of the blackboard there
could be coordinates coming out it could
be any dimensional and it's described by
some coordinates let's call them x
if i really were just doing two two
variables i might just talk about x and
y
but i want to be more general and so
what i'll talk about is x1
x2
x3 as many as i need to describe the
space and how many do i need i need as
many as there are dimensions of space
so let's call the dimension of space d
this will go up to x d
that's how many coordinates
the horizontal one could be x1 the
vertical one could be x2 the one
sticking out of the blackboard that you
can't see would be x3 and so forth
all right now suppose we had some
function
that was a function
of the x's
you can think of it as a field if you
like something which just varies from
place to place
let's call it phi of x
x now stands for for the collection x1
through xd
i won't bother writing that it's a
function of x1 x2 x3 just a function of
x and i'm calling it 5 or
i don't know why i'm calling it phi
now let's consider the change in phi the
change in the value of phi
when you move a small
distance
and let's characterize that distance a
small infinitesimal distance
infinitesimal just means really small
let's characterize that displacement
that infinite displacement by a
differential dx
this stands for a small displacement
this really means
dx1
dx2 all right so here would be dx1
here would be dx2
and if this vector
pointed out into the x3 direction that
would be at the x3 so just like x stands
for this collection of things
dx stands for small displacement of all
the coordinates
then how much does phi change
in going from this point to that point
what's the change in phi the change in
phi we call d phi
the small change in phi it's obviously
related to the partial derivatives of
phi
with respect to the coordinates i'm
going to write the answer
it's just given
by the small change in phi
if you moved purely in the x1 direction
times the small change in dx1
plus
d phi by d x two the small change in phi
if you move purely in the second
direction
first term is the change in phi if you
move this way second change is the
second term is the change in phi moving
that way
times dx2
plus dot dot dot as many terms as there
are
until you get up to the d term
this is i don't even know what rule
that's called does that got a name
i don't know what it's called
i don't know if it has a name or not
yeah if you divide by dp over there you
get a dx dt you know so basically it's
the chain list
well it's it's part of the chain rule
yeah uh but yeah
it is connected to the chain rule yeah
all right now we're going to introduce
some notation this is standard notation
many of you have seen it before
when you have a sum like this
a sum and in particular a sum when the
index is repeated like this
we can rewrite that first of all even if
it weren't the index repeated we could
first of all rewrite this
as the sum over n
where n goes from one to d
from one
to the total dimension of space
the derivative of phi
with respect to x n
times d x n
that's just that sum just stands for the
sum of these terms
and then since it happens so many times
that you'll have sums over n of things
with repeated indices are repeated
simply means twice in the same
expression it doesn't mean three times
it doesn't mean five times
if
you see a sum with a repeated index
einstein's summation convention
uh
would i say this was one of the more
brilliant things for anybody else this
would probably would have been one of
the more brilliant things that they did
clever things
he was not a man who wasn't known for
his uh for that kind of cleverness
particularly but he said i got tired of
writing this over and over i'm just
going to leave out the symbol
this automatically means
that you sum
over the index n so defined by the x1
times the x1 and so forth and so on
the sum
adding them up whenever you see a thing
let me write another one supposing i had
an expression b sub n c sub n whatever b
and c are i don't know what b and c are
whatever they happen to be summed on n
from n equals one to d
we'll simply write that as
b and
c n c n b n
and then leave out the summation sign
the only thing we have to be careful
about
oh incidentally
it doesn't matter what whether we use n
there n is a summation variable it's
called a dummy index it's not one it's
not two it's just sum over one two three
and four
we could call it if we like
exactly the same thing sum over r
or sum over m
when you're summing over an index
it's just a notation that says sum over
it it doesn't matter what you what you
actually call it
all right you just mustn't call it
something which appears somewhere else
in the equation
give it a name the summation index but
make sure that it isn't the name that
appears someplace else in the equation
because then you get confused
okay so that's the summation convention
and
the summation convention and the
differential change in a field when you
move from one point to another
now there's another
another rule this is the second rule
which we will use over and over and this
is about all we'll use over and over
a second rule
and it has to do with change of
coordinates
change of coordinates in particular
going from one set of curvy linear
coordinates to another but that doesn't
matter right now
we have a set of coordinates which i've
called x
but now let's suppose i use another set
of coordinates that i call y
and the y's are different coordinates so
we have some coordinate chart there's
our coordinate chart
but
or our coordinate map if you like
but now i'm going to introduce other
coordinates
and these other coordinates could be
strange curved ones if i like or not
there's another set of coordinates and
i'm going to call those y
and the rule of course is
that if you know what x is if you know
the collection of x's at a point that
determines a point
then there's a definite rule about what
the values of y's are that's what a
coordinate transformation is
a rule for going from one set of
coordinates x one through x n for a
particular point to another set of
coordinates and so that means that the
y's they also go from there also a
collection of them
y sub let's call it n again
y sub n
is some function let's just call it y
sub n of all of the x's
in other words if you know all the x's i
can tell you what all of the y's are if
i want y one
some particular function of the x's
which is y one if i want y two likewise
and so on and this of course is called
the coordinate transformation yeah
so getting back to the original equation
uh for the infinitesimal movements uh
yeah do you know what kind of uh
assumptions are being baked in about
non-commutation relations
or infinitesimal movements is there's
two perspective quantum mechanics when
you do that oh
that's uh
let's not get into quantum mechanics now
that uh that's a separate issue i
thought you were going to ask me about
second-order quantities
that was the other part of it but
yeah uh we're assuming we're assuming
all numbers commute all expressions
commute okay for sure
as far as second order quantities
this is a fir this equation is first
order in small quantities
all right and that's what the d means as
opposed to delta
delta would mean an actual finite
difference
uh and then of course it would be more
complicated with higher orders and delta
yeah
there's some restrictions on what a
coordinate system can be so that it's
actually one value yeah yeah absolutely
absolutely every point has a unique set
of coordinates and every
every point has a unique set of x ones
and x through x n's likewise with the
y's and every
set of x's
if i give you an x1 through an xn
that uniquely picks out a point
a point in the space let's call it p
and likewise if i give you a point
that uniquely gives me a set of
coordinates that's the assumption
of a coordinate frame
and uh the same should be true for the
y's so that means that there should be a
one-to-one correspondence
between x's and y's is that was that the
question
oh for sure yes we're certainly going to
assume continuity differentiability
uh and smoothness of everything
that is uh
we're going to assume everything is as
smooth as you ever need it to be so that
you can differentiate differentiate
again differentiate again and never run
into anything singular so yes that's uh
that's another aspect
the
x's
and the y's are smoothly related to each
other as smooth as we ever need
depending on the circumstances so that
means continuous
differentiable maybe even differentiable
twice and so forth
okay now here's the question
supposing i know
the derivative of phi
with respect to all of the x's x m
for all the m's
in other words i know the set of partial
derivatives of phi at a point
we pick a particular point and supposing
i know at that point
how 5 varies with respect to x's
i want to ask how it varies with respect
to y
i would like to compute the derivative
of phi
with respect to
y sub n
and i'm going to write down the answer
if you don't know this
if you don't know this i ask you please
look look this up this is a tool that we
will use over and over and over again
it is a kind of chain rule it's a
kind of chain rule
what you do is you first differentiate
phi
with respect
to the x's
and then you differentiate the x's
with respect to the y
on the left hand side i've picked let's
let's uh let's see what this means in
with precision or not with precision
but uh in in very concrete terms
for example what this would say is pick
an n
let's pick n equals one
this would say the derivative of phi
with respect to y one
is a sum of terms note the repeated
indices here so let's write it out
explicitly
this means
derivative of phi with respect to x1
times the change in x1
with respect to y1
all right plus
notice
y1
i've chosen n equals 1 over here plus
the change in phi
when i change x2 a little bit
times the change in x2
oops x2 when i change
y1
plus dot dot dot
the change
in phi when i change y1
is given by a sum
the shift in phi when i change x1
times the change in x1 when i change y1
plus the change in phi when i change x2
times the change in x2 when i change y1
and so forth and so on dot dot dot
up to the last term
all right
that's what this means i could do the
same thing with y2 the change in phi
when i change y2 a little bit
we just have to change the index of the
y not the x's they're summed over
and so on
what's this formula what's this called
you know anybody know i don't know i
don't remember what the name of these
rules are
this is a this is a form of chain rule
yes
okay so let's write it generally the
change in phi when you change any
component of y
is related to the changes of phi when
you change x
just by
this simple formula and we can get rid
of all of this
and all we have to do is remember the
einstein summation convention
on the right side m because it's
repeated is a dummy index it's not one
it's not two it's summed over
but in which is not summed over on
either side
you get to choose you can choose n
equals 1 you can choose n equals 2 you
can choose n equals 3. it's not summed
over
and so this is a formula which sort of
summarizes
all of the derivatives of phi with
respect to y in terms of the derivatives
of phi with respect to x
all right let's uh let's put these two
rules up on the blackboard somewheres
because as i said they're our
fundamental tool
for making coordinate transformations
we're interested in coordinate
transformations
because we want to be able to go from
things like curved coordinates to
straight coordinates for exactly this
reason that we want to explore how
gravity changes when we change our
coordinates from curved to straight or
other or things like that things of that
nature
in fact in a general space which is
curve which is itself curved a space
like the surface of a sphere or the
surface of a saddle there is nothing
comparable to the rectangular
cartesian coordinates of flat space
we just lay out arbitrary coordinates
and we have to express everything in
terms of a set of coordinates which has
no preferred special nice straightness
in a curved space or curved space time
and so it's important to learn how to go
from one set of coordinates to another
since none of them are particularly
preferred
in fact we're going to want to express
the laws of physics in a way which
really doesn't depend on the coordinates
but unfortunately there's no way to
write equations without putting some
coordinates into them
so we need to explore how you go from
one set of coordinates to another and
that's the basic tool of general
relativity
all right so let's put down the two
important facts
the change in a variable
when you move from one point to another
is equal to
a
partial derivative of phi with respect
to x m or x let's call it x m
dxm
summation convention implied
that's one thing and the other is that
the derivative of phi with respect to
let's call it
yn
can be re-expressed
as a sum
of derivatives of phi with respect to x
n
m
times the x m
by d y n
these are our two governing
little simple formulas
are you assuming the dimensions stay the
same what's that between x and y are the
dimensions
yeah
yeah i mean if we need uh
if we need three uh coordinates to
locate a point in three dimensional
space
it's not going to get only two
coordinates or six coordinates if we
change coordinate systems so right so
the number of coordinates
is simply the dimension of the space
can you say the second equation
what's that can you say the second
equation is false
it probably does i'm sure it does
i'm sure it does uh
yeah sure we can
just change it does
and indeed it does
all right
but i want to write them both down
because we'll be going we'll be using
them
regularly
okay
now tensors what are tensors
tensors are things which have components
like
and vectors
components change when you go from one
set of coordinates to another
just as a simple example of a coordinate
transformation let's just do something
we're familiar with
let's take uh a coordinate
transformation from coordinates which
look like this
rectangular coordinates to another set
of coordinates which also is rectangular
just by rotating the coordinates as an
example
there's another set of coordinates
superimposed on top of the first
and the red ones we can call y the uh
black ones we can call x
and now let's take a vector
do i have another color let's see if i
have another color
let's take a vector
there's a particular vector
and that can is that color visible
yeah everybody everybody's fine with
purple okay
that's some specific vector all right it
has components
it's components we just get in
rectangular coordinates
we just get its components by dropping
perpendiculars to the axes
and the two of the horizontal the two
components the x component and the y
component if it's sticking out of the
blackboard there's also a z component
but we simply drop perpendiculars from
the tip of the vector
down to the coordinate axes and that
defines the components in a in a
familiar way and of course the
components depend on which coordinates
we're using the coordinates of this
vector
in the y frame of reference
is gotten again by dropping
perpendiculars to the axes but they're
different axes
so the components of a vector do depend
in general they depend curvy linear or
not curvy linear they do depend on the
coordinate frame
and there are rules that you can work
out easily we're going to talk about
them
for relating the coordinates of a vector
in one frame of reference to the
coordinates another frame of reference
if we have some
vector equation an equation that some
vector is equal to some other vector
then the only way to express it with
equations is to express it in terms of
components but we want to make sure
that's an equation which is true in all
reference frames and so we have to know
how to go back and forth the components
of things all right so a vector is one
thing which has coordinate components
and how many components does a vector
have
again in a d-dimensional space
in a d-dimensional space
you can think d equals 3 if you like but
in a d-dimensional space the number of
components that a vector has is d
uh
a vector is a special case of a tensor
it's a tensor with only one index or a
tensor of rank one
all right
a simpler thing which is also a tensor
but which is even simpler is a scalar
a scalar is a quantity which really
doesn't have components it doesn't have
a sense of directionality
it's just a number a numerical value
it doesn't have any components when i
write down the scalar phi let's suppose
that pi is a scalar it doesn't have to
be in that equation but let's suppose
the phi is a scalar
then that scalar has a numerical value
at every point and then like for example
the temperature the temperature in space
doesn't depend on whether i choose
coordinates one way or the other
it's a scalar
but it's a special case of a tensor and
it's a tensor with no indices it has no
indices at all
it's a tensor of rank zero
a vector is a tensor of rank one
we're going to explore quantities which
are tensors with any number of indices
uh and these things are more obscure
they're harder to understand um
uh
geometrically but eventually you'll get
familiar with them and the rules for
them we can work out by starting the
best place to start
well the best place to start is with
scalars let's start with scalars and
talk about how they transform from frame
of reference to frame of reference
well the answer is they don't they stay
the same
so we would write that we could write
that in the following
well
the following
notation
the field phi
in
conventions in which we use coordinates
y to describe it let's call it phi of y
is equal
to phi of x
if
x and y here label the same point
this is the expression for phi
in the x-coordinates these are the
x-coordinates
here's the y-coordinates laid down i'm
going to draw them over here
there's the y-coordinates
and let's suppose that this point and
this point really are the same point
then there's only one value of phi it's
the value of phi at that point
and the transformation property of a
scalar is trivial
nothing happens to it
uh
the temperature at a point of space
doesn't depend on which way the
coordinate axes or even if you're using
curved coordinates
and so this is the transformation
property
of a scalar okay
now let's come to a vector
how do the components of a vector
transform when you go from one frame of
reference to another
we need to start with some vector we
need some quantity which is a vector and
a simple vector perhaps in many respects
the simplest vector the primordial
vector in a sense is a little
displacement
a little displacement namely the thing
that we already called d phi the dx
excuse me
dx
represents
a vector
and we can put an arrow on top of it to
indicate that it's a vector
it's nice to indicate vectors by arrows
and it simply means a little
differential displacement
it's a sort of quintessential vector a
little small displacement
okay
now it has components this stands for
the vector itself the vector itself is a
geometric object
it has components the components of it
are just
dx1 dx2
the x3
and so forth in other words the
components of it are
just the little displacements
in the x-coordinate frame
so again if this is the x-coordinate
frame
and this is the x
then these dx's are just the little
displacements of the origin of the of
the coordinates themselves
all right that same vector can be
described in y-coordinates the same
physical vector think of the vector as a
little stick with a pointer on it
that same physical vector has components
in the y-coordinate frame and the
question is how do we find them
those components are
starting at this point and ending at
this point
they are
the components are
d y one
i've written it as a for three
dimensional space but as many as you
like
it's the same vector
but with the components being expressed
relative to two different coordinate
systems
what's the relationship between them
well
let's suppose we go from one point to
another and let me focus remember these
y's here are all functions of x
and the x's are also functions of the
y's they're functions of each other the
x's and y's are functions of each other
let's concentrate on dy1 over here
what's the change in y1
when i change x by a little bit
for that i use the top equation
except phi now being replaced by y1
the change in y1
now we're just going to repeat that
equation is the derivative of y1
with respect to xm
dxm
get it the change in y1 i'm just using
that exact formula up on the top except
with phi being
y1
the change in y1
when i move in x space a little bit is
just the derivative of y with respect to
x times the change in x
summed over
m what if i were changing y2 well what
would be the change in y2 when i go from
one point to another
i just right just replace
put two up
here what if i pick a generic
index n
then it just becomes
the differential displacement
in y in
is just the derivative of y n with
respect to x m times d x m
right well
this tells me explicitly how the
components of the small vector transform
they transform
by getting multiplied by this collection
of things d y by d x
now i can tell you what the definition
of a
contravariant vector is
the definition of a contravarian vector
is a collection of things which have
components in both the x
frame of reference
and also components in the y frame of
reference
and those components let's now be gener
general let's call it v
v for vector
the components of the vector v one
through v n
in the y frame of reference let me put
down here in brackets
that these are the components relative
to the y frame of reference
in other words relative to the
y-coordinate system
are equal
to the derivatives of y n
with respect to x m
times v
m
in the x coordinate frame in other words
they behave exactly the same way as
these little differential
vector components of a little
displacement behave that's that don't
ask me why this is true this is
definition
this is definition of an object which
transforms
contravariantly
it's just a word it doesn't
for our purposes it doesn't mean
anything right now
that's the definition
of a vector
or a contravarian vector that its
components whatever they are that they
transform when you go from one frame of
reference to another
through this collection of quantities
the x the y n by d x m how many
quantities like there are are there all
together
how many
d squared right any y can be
differentiated with respect to any x er
yes and so there are d squared such
coefficient functions here
and this is the way you transform a
vector
to those who are familiar with linear
algebra this is of course a matrix
and this is a column vector and here's a
column vector but we don't need that
right now this is the transformation
property of a contravariant vector
variant referred to the nature of the
coordinate system no it refers to the
way it transforms the way it transforms
that's right
the way it transforms we're gonna we're
going to discover other objects called
covariant uh
tensors but for so far this is just a
mere vector something that's pretty easy
to visualize
now a tensor of rank two
is an object which is not so easy to
visualize
you should think of it somehow as having
two directions so that's a thing that
has built into it two directions instead
of one
but there's an easy way to think about
this the simplest
tensor that's made up
uh the simplest tensor of rank two can
be simply thought of as a product of two
vectors
given two vectors
and they could be the same vector or
they could be different vectors it
doesn't matter let's call one of them a
and it has components m a sub a
m
and now let's take another vector which
we'll call b
and write its components
down how many such product how many such
things are there altogether
i can multiply there's a whole
collection of objects i can make i can
make up
i can take any one of the components of
a and multiply it by any one of the
components of b and that's an object
it's an object that may or may not be
interesting we're going to see we're
going to discover ones which are
interesting how many such components
does such an object have
this has d components this has
decomponents
the number of components all together is
d squared
so this is an object
which has
d squared components
and the individual components are
labeled with two directions
this is a special case of a tensor of
rank
two
it has two components sorry it has two
indices
and altogether
d squared individual components
how does it transform when i change
coordinate systems well this is easy i
already know
how
the vectors transform
so all i need to do is
let's uh let's work it out
let's work it out
let's take
a
let's
compute
a
n
a m a-m-b-n
in the y
in the y-frame of reference
in other words where the coordinates are
written relative to the y-frame of
reference
well here's a rule for connecting
components of a vector in the frame with
components of the same vector in the x
frame so let's just apply it
let's relate these now first of all
there's a
a is a vector are not dummy indices
they're picked this could be three this
could be two
but they're not summed over dummy index
is one which is summed over
all right so here's the matching
this index matches this index so we
better put an m up here
and then we differentiate it with
respect to a dummy index i don't want to
call a dummy index in now so i'll call
it x r
times
a r
that's just this piece of it over here
am of y this should be of x
am
in the y frame of reference
is the derivative of y m with respect to
x r times a r
summed over r
now that's only half the expression the
other half
involves what happens to b so let's
write that down
again
we should match indices
here we have the nth index so that means
some derivative of y
n
now i need another dummy index
i need another dummy index i've already
summed over r i can't call it r again so
i'll call it
s
x s
times d x
times
a
times b
s
in the x reference frame
all i've done
is taken a and b and separately
transformed them from the x coordinates
to the y coordinates
but now let me just regroup it
let me just regroup it by taking this
over here
and writing a r
x
a m times b n
is called tmn a tensor of 12 of rank 2
with index m and n
so i can call this then
t m n
with components in the y frame of
reference
that's equal to
the y m
by d x r
the y n
by d x s
and what shall i call this
it's also some t it's also the
components
of a tensor built up out of a times b
okay
not tmn but trs
trs
the first entry has to do with a the
second entry has to do with b so i
should really i should really invert the
order of them
b
s
x just to make it look the same as on
this side and then what do we see on the
right hand side on the right hand side
we have t r s
evaluated or its components in the x
frame of reference
so this little operation
has defined for me a new class of things
which are tensors of rank two
which transform in this manner
notice it's very similar
except sort of doubled
each time you want to transform an index
you get a factor dy by dx
for each index
here's the index m
you have the the y m by d x r and this
is a dummy index
and then for the n you'll have a d y n
by d x s
and then it multiplies the t
with the rs index in the other frame of
reference this is a pattern
you get you could do the same thing for
tensors with any number of indices up
here
i'll leave it to you to work out the
rules they're easy they're just simple
generalizations of this where for every
index you get another factor like this
and another index up in the tensor over
here
that's all a tensor is that's the whole
definition of a tensor these tensors are
generally functions of position
they're functions of position in general
just like vectors
can be vector fields and vary from place
to place
uh
but this is the rule for transforming
tensors and that's all there is to it
there's no other definition of a tensor
than this
uh
and we're going to see some examples of
them
rather than try to give you a deep
geometric insight into them
i think we'll work with them for a while
get familiar with the machinery for them
but we're going to see some examples of
them
okay so that's the definition
of
a
tensor
with contravariant components
we're going to come to what a covariant
tensor is and you'll understand the
difference but all of these indices are
transforming the same way
uh they're they're transforming with
coefficients d y by dx
not the x by d y but the y by dx when
you want a thing and the y frame on the
left hand side
then it's the y by the x on the right
hand side times t x
all right that's the definition of
tensors
with all contravariant indices
next
let's see should we take a break or
should we take a break in another 10
minutes
a question on this
can you make those rearrangements right
uh you made a lot of assumptions about
the map behind it by the tensors
right
well i mean you you're assuming that
commutative and it's not a cross product
not a dot product yeah no this is just
numerical multiplications
yeah
there's nothing um
you can
you can invert the order of anything
times anything else as long as you're
just multiplying numbers
and each expression on the blackboard is
a number
i think there are some some assumptions
the matrices should be invertible
right
i mean these these i never
these are matrices and they are
invertible
the assumption that they're invertible
is equivalent to the statement that
there's one-to-one mapping
from x to y and from y to x
that you can invert the coordinates
that you have
your first rule is basically a total
differential
and that means it has to be exact
yeah
that just means it's a function it means
it has a value everywhere well defined
value everywhere that's all
well
no
it means that the partials have to have
good quality no
well assuming everything is
differentiable that's all you have to
assume twice differentiable
twice differentiable and they they can
mix
and what you can switch the order and
you can switch the order of
differentiation then you're good
right
all right let's uh spend a few more
minutes and come to the i spend a few
more minutes with the idea of a
covariant vector
the top thing
d phi
is the archetype of a
contravariant vector
d phi or sorry dx dx is the archetype of
a contravariant vector
it has components and its components are
simply this
here's another object with components
how many components does it have it's
the collection of partial derivatives of
phi
it also has d components has the same
number of components
as the x here
it's also an object that one could call
a vector insofar as it has components
but it's a geometrically different kind
of thing
it's not a displacement but it's the
gradient of a function it's the rate of
change of a function along different
directions
an object like this
is called a covariant vector
more precisely the
they're called the covariant components
of a covariant vector
covariant components of a vector
but
we can also ask
given a collection of objects defined by
the
the xn here they are defined by dxm
here's a collection in the x frame of
reference
how do they transform
in other words if i gave you
this covariant vector
namely defined by the x the collection
of components
how do i calculate d phi by d y well
here's the rule
here's the rule right here i don't need
to go any further
and i can abstract from this rule
a more general idea of a covariant
vector
instead of taking
d phi by dxm
let's just call let's just define an
object to be a covariant vector
if it transforms in the following way
i guess i can use the same letters
i'll use the same letters but now we're
talking
upside down what's that it's kind of the
same thing as the yes yes yes we're
going to compare the two in a minute
all right so here is a
i'm going to put its index downstairs
why
just because it looks nice this is down
lower than
but there's a real reason there's a real
point there's a real point we'll come to
it for a moment in a moment but when you
write contra sorry covariant indices you
always write them downstairs when you
write contravariant indices you always
write them upstairs
the difference between the covariant and
the contravariant are how things
transform so here's an example
of a covariant object
which it's just a definition now that we
put the index downstairs
it turns out to be a nice definition
a nice uh notation it's a notation it's
not a definition
a sub n in the y frame of reference
its components in the y frame of
reference
are equal
to the x m by d y n
times
a
sub m
in the x frame of reference
these are the components in the y frame
these are the components in the x frame
the phi by dx is the component of a in
the x frame divided by the y in the y
frame
all i've done is abstract out of this
replace the phi by the y by a
and divide by the x also by a and this
now defines a class of objects which may
be maybe more general than just
gradients
any object whose transformation property
is like this
is called a covariant vector
now let's just look at the difference
between the transformation properties of
covariant and contravariant vectors
let's
i'll use this as my
typical
contravarian vector and now let's write
the corresponding thing for the
covariant vector a n in the y frame of
reference
is now equal to
d x by d y
n
m or let's call it r
i guess we can call it m
times a
m
in the x frame of reference
notice the difference
one of them
involves the set of derivatives d y by d
x
the other involves a set of derivatives
the x by b y
notice that there's a very nice pattern
here
the index upstairs
is upstairs
on both sides of the equation
and when you contract or when you sum
over indices using the einstein
summation convention it's always an
upper index with a lower index
that's a general rule
that when you sum over indices
you should be summing over indices one
upstairs and one downstairs
there's something wrong with your
equations
if you're identifying indices and
summing with both of them either
upstairs or downstairs
but thus far
it's just a notational device
and we see it has that pattern that a
thing which is downstairs on the left is
also downstairs on the right and when we
sum over a dummy index
it's always an upper one with a lower
one which is a sort of cancellation an
upper one cancels a lower one and gets
rid of it so to speak
that's the pattern
there's no theorem here it's just an
observation about uh about these
equations
and
these are the two transformation
properties
and once
i have the idea about how a covariant
vector transforms
i can define objects which have several
covariant indices
covariant indices mean indices
downstairs
i'll give you an example
same deal
exactly the same deal i go through the
same thing except with covariant indices
and let's see if we can figure out or
guess what the transformation properties
of a
tensor with two covariant indices
all right so now it's two covariant
indices
this is the y
and the y frame of reference we have to
turn the derivatives upside down
they become the x by d y
instead of the y by dx
and on the right hand side we also
should have lower indices rs
x
we have a tensor with two downstairs you
know incidentally i don't believe i've
ever in my life heard a physicist
actually refer to covariant indices in
contravariant indices we just come
upstairs and downstairs
because nobody can ever remember which
is which
i looked it up tonight so i get it right
but every time i do uh
it's i i forget the next time
incidentally what do i have here let's
put the indices in
there's lower indices here better mean
there are upper indices here if we're
going to sum over them
and there's lower indices here so there
better be an m and an n
oh r sorrow s thank you
you know what i think it is i think
um
partial derivatives uh are in some sense
uh like basis vectors
yeah
and so varying
like the basis vectors is covariant
that's where that terminology comes from
perhaps
we're a country kings are minimum
um
but you can check the pattern of these
things there's always a pattern to them
when you sum over indices it's an
upstairs where the downstairs
upstairs were downstairs the left hand
side here has downstairs indices m and n
and uh so it's not too hard to keep
track of
and by inspection you can see whether
your equations
make good sense in this respect
okay
let's take a break and then we'll come
to the metric tensor
the metric tensor itself the metric
tensor is a tensor
and it's an important one
okay let's get started
um i'm going i i think i'm going slowly
i hope i'm going slowly
i'm going intentionally slowly
which means i'm telling i'm telling you
things that many of you already know
but i'm going at a rate which uh
uh which i'm hoping
will carry along the majority of you
we now want to come
to the idea of a metric tensor
let's begin
with ordinary conventional i will call
it by its right name flat space
incidentally
let's distinguish two things
there are
flat there is flat space who which i
have not defined for you yet but the
table top here is a flat space the
blackboard is a flat space
the surface of a sphere is not a flat
space
and there are
flat coordinates
flat coordinates usually are taken to
mean when people speak about flat
coordinates it's usually uh it's a music
it's an abuse of language but what they
mean is rectilinear um pretty much
cartesian coordinates sometimes spoken
of as flat coordinates
the
axes are not curved the axes are flat
and so forth
so we can speak of flat coordinates and
we can speak of flat space times or flat
spaces for the moment
all we're doing is space now not space
time
quite a distinct concept
you can introduce as i will
we will do it we can introduce for the
discussion of flat space
there's nothing to prevent us from using
curvy linear coordinates on it
on the other hand there's no clear
concept of flat coordinates on curved
space
curved space you can coordinate it you
can lay down coordinates on it but
there's no sense in which there in which
one set of coordinates is any straighter
than the other set of coordinates
and so i thought i would just point that
out to you
uh
in a curved space
it's basically a space which has an
obstruction in it the mathematical
obstruction
to using flat coordinates
this word obstruction i'm using over and
over again and i want you i do want you
to think of it as being related to the
obstruction
in removing a gravitational field by
changing coordinates
uh
here in geometry it's a question of
whether well let's let's write down
let's write down what the metric is
first and then i'll tell you exactly
what it's an obstruction to what
curvature is an obstruction to
uh
does everybody know what i mean by the
word obstruction i mean a mathematical
property that forbids you from doing
something to simplify a situation in a
certain way
okay
let's start with flat space
i'll draw it of course as
two-dimensional and i will introduce
some coordinates
and i'm going to take the simplest set
of coordinates cartesian coordinates
it is not important for us whether
they're tilted this way or that way we
can rotate the coordinates
but let's take a infinitesimal vector
dx
and think of the length of the vector
all right i'm going to take the square
of the length of the vector in two
dimensions we can just drop
perpendiculars and rewrite the length of
the vector in terms of the components
this is of course also true in higher
dimensions
three four five dimensions
and we use the pythagoras the
pythagorean theorem
let's call the length of the vector
let's call it d s
it's also small
so it's also differential
and this and the pythagorean theorem
for two dimensions here
would say that the square
it's just the square of the hypotenuse
we'll call it ds squared is equal
in this case
to dx1
squared
plus dx
squared now please let's not confuse
notation
these
superscripts over here are labeling
which coordinate we're talking about
this superscript over here literally
means square
dx2 here does not mean anything squared
it just means the second coordinate this
means the first coordinate so i'm
putting them in brackets just so you'll
know
if i didn't put them in brackets you
would think it was dx12 or dx22 so i put
them in brackets
that's the pythagorean theorem if there
were more coordinates in a higher
dimensional space and we were using
cartesian coordinates
we would write
dx
squared here and so forth
okay let me write this in another way
for you
uh
which is sort of slightly contrived i
don't know maybe it's not so contrived
um
first of all i can write it in this
fashion
d x m
d x
m
now
this is violating one of my rules about
repeated
indices my rule about repeated indices
is that you should put one upstairs and
one downstairs
okay so i am explicitly
violating that rule
but in order to
i'll just remind myself that that it
really means sum over m
and this means the x1 squared plus the
x2 squared plus dx3 squared
and as i said i've explicitly violated a
rule which i set out but i want to
restore that rule
i want to rewrite the same equation in a
way which restores the rule
and so i'm going to invent a new symbol
what's the new symbol anybody know what
it is
not ada
chronicle delta
right
right eta is the other symbol that i
could have but
the mathematical symbol
delta m n
that mathematical symbol has the
following meaning
it is how many how many components does
it have altogether
d squared
each m and each n it has a value
its value is equal to its numerical
value
is equal to one
if and only if
iff means if and only if m is equal to n
in other words delta 1 1 delta 2 2 delta
3 3
are all equal to 1.
and it's equal to zero
if and only if
m is not equal
to n
so that means delta one one
is equal to one delta two two is equal
to one delta 33 is equal to 1.
delta 1 2 is equal to 0. delta 1 3 is
equal to 0. delta 3 2 is equal to 0.
that's the meaning of the symbol
mathematical symbol
and you know it's
it's partly some interesting mathematics
and partly simply notation
a notational device
uh
to be used
to simplify equations
all right now i can rewrite this
in the following form notice i've put
these indices downstairs
all right i'm going to rewrite this as
equal to delta
m n with two downstairs indices
d x m
d x n with two upstairs indices
let's see what this thing means
it means or an m and n are both
summation indices now they're both
summation indices
one upstairs and one downstairs one
upstair one downstairs one upstairs one
downstairs one upstairs
so this now conforms to my
rule
about the way that you combine indices
together
if you want to sum over a repeated indic
index make sure one is upstairs and one
is downstairs now what does this give
you
well every time m is equal to n
delta mn is one
so that gives you things like delta dx1
squared plus the x2 squared plus dx3
squared and so forth
in other words when m is equal to n
you get a dx squared
and you get one for each
numerical value of m
okay what about when m is not equal to n
are there any terms in here with dx1
times dx2
no because delta 1 2 is equal to 0.
so this expression here
that's the purpose of delta m n
is to pick out
the contributions when this m is equal
to this n and that means just summing
the squares of the of the dx's that's
what a delta m in and it simply restores
the rule
writing it in this way restores the rule
that uh that you
when you use the summation convention
you should always be
uh summing over one upper and one lower
index
all right so here's a neat
form
for the s squared
delta m n the x m the x n
but now i want to write this
i want to write the length of this
vector
not in x-coordinate
excuse me
not in x-coordinates but in
y-coordinates
the same little vector
the same precise little vector which has
exactly the same length but i want to
write it now in terms of the
differential displacements in
some other coordinates
in particular i have in mind
curvy linear coordinates of some kind
so let's rewrite the same expression
what we need
is a formula
let's let's erase a blackboard here
we need a formula for dx
m
for example this one over here
in terms of
d y's
if i had that i could plug it into here
and re-express this in terms of the d
y's
so what do we know about dxm
for that we use the top formula up on up
on top let's see
um
except with x's being replaced replacing
y's
i'm going to write the formula i think
you'll all recognize it
the change in x m
when i
when i move from one point to another
uh
is equal
to the derivative of x m
with respect to y r
d y r
this is an application
of the rule up on top
except where there are y's here instead
of x's
and where the thing which is changing
defy
is just x m
same rule a change in a certain quantity
is the derivative of the quantity with
respect to y times the change in y
summed over the components
all right so that's that's all we need
to do now
we can now rewrite
this
distance
in y notation
let's do it
here it is d s squared
is equal
all right let's see what we have
delta m n
that's this now we have dxm that's this
partial of x m with respect to y r
times d y r but i'll write the d y r in
a moment i don't want to write it down
yet yeah let's put it over here
d y r
but now
we also have to put in dx in
so that's going to be partial
of x n with respect to y s
times d y s
now look what i have
i have an expression for d s squared
that involves some
complicated collection of functions
first of all
m and n are dummy indices
they're summed over
the things which really this depends on
are r and s
the left the right hand side doesn't
depend on m and n they're summed over
but it does depend on r and s
so let's give this a name this quantity
this whole quantity here
it has a value for each r and each s
but it's summed over in m n
i'm going to give it the name g
r s
notice that it has lower indices indices
below the fraction bar here
grs
it's a function of position in general
let's call it a y
it doesn't matter whether we call it a
function of x or y since if we know
something as a function of x we
automatically know as a function of y
but i want to be working in y notation
so i call this g r s of y and in general
it depends on y it's not just a
collection of numbers is there a
collection of functions
g r s of y times d y
s
d y
r
what's the lesson the oh
of course this is a special case
or this is similar
it also contains the x's times the x's
but
it contains the kronecker delta
here we have a very similar thing
except instead of the kronecker delta we
have a collection of again
d squared coefficients
for each r in each s there's a g
it's no longer true
that the g
one ones
are equal to one and the g two twos are
equal to one they're not they're all
whatever they are
nor is it true that g one two is equal
to
zero this is called the metric tensor
this is the metric tensor
and it's a thing with two lower indices
two covariant indices and it's actually
easy to prove
it's quite easy to prove
that it transformed in fact i'll prove
it in a moment now
it's easy to prove that it actually
transforms as a covariant tensor
how can we do that i started in this
case here
with something i knew very well just
pythagoras theorem
in cartesian coordinates
that led me to introduce let's call it
now the metric tensor in cartesian
coordinates
this is the metric tensor in cartesian
coordinates i just read it off from
pythagoras theorem
and then i changed coordinates to
another set of coordinates
and found out that the only thing that
happens
is the delta mn is replaced by a g
which depends in general on position
okay
incidentally for this case
where i started with the with the
blackboard flat blackboard when i say
blackboard when i started with a flat
space
we know although it might not be obvious
from this form
i might give you some form like this
whether it's obvious or not we know that
we can always transform it back to this
form
to this form that looks like cartesian
coordinates
we'll come back to that in a minute but
what about the general transformation
properties of this thing which i'm
calling a covariant tensor
how can we work them out
well here's the way and let's start
with a general expression
among the x components
let's not assume that the space that
we're talking about is either flat or
that the coordinates are
cartesian
right that means that we should start
with a more general expression here
in which this is g
m n
of x
in other words we should make it look
more or less like it looks on this side
over here
in our starting form
let's suppose we did that
then
d s squared would be given by this
general form over here
but
on this side we would just replace the
delta m n
by g m n of x
what have i shown
i've shown that the grs
in y notation the y components
are given by the x components
times the standard dx by d y
coefficients
this is exactly the transformation
property of a covariant tensor of rank
two
so the metric tensor
is a
covariant tensor of rank two
if i give you a general space a general
space i mean it could be curved it could
have geometric properties which are not
the geometric properties of a flat plane
it could be the surface of a sphere
surface of a saddle
we can always write the metric
the metric tensor or the distance
between neighboring points
can always be written in this form
the question is under what circumstances
can we find a coordinate transformation
from y
to x
so that
this can be brought back to the form
delta m n in other words is there some
if i were to have given you
the y coordinates and i would have given
you the description of the distance
between every neighboring point in this
form here
that's equivalent to telling you what
the geometry is like
if you know the distance between every
pair of neighboring points
if i were to give you grs of y and i
gave you this general form i can ask the
question is there some core does there
exist a coordinate transformation
which will bring it back to this form
which looks like cartesian coordinates
and flat blackboard
in two dimensions or in three
dimensions if the answer is yes
in other words that this complicated grs
of y can be undone by coordinate
transformation and brought to the form
of cartesian coordinates in flat space
then the space is called flat
it means
that you may have chosen
complicated curvy linear coordinates
but there's no obstruction to
straightening out those coordinates and
writing it in the form of flat space
that's the definition of a flat space
a flat riemannian space the term is
romanian refers to this kind of geometry
that there exists a coordinate
transformation
that will flatten out the metric
and turn it just into this collection of
zeros and ones
in other words that it will restore the
standard flat space form of
of the
of the relationship between points
neighboring points
if not
that means there is no way there is no
coordinate transformation which will
undo
and get rid of
the uh the spatial variation the
complexity of this the fact that this
varies from space to space and so on
that point
will not bring you back to this cannot
get back to that the space is called
curved
curvature in that sense is an
obstruction an obstruction to removing
the curvy linearity of the coordinates
if you like
in that sense yeah
i think i understand
my understanding
if
if you have a coordinate system that's
not
cartesian right but you can convert it
into this contour delta then yeah then
it's
flat then it's flat
right
that's right if you can't then it's
called curved
now it's possible that a space be
flat in some spaces in some places and
not in others for example this table top
could be connected to something over
here which was a spherical dome or
something
in that case what is true
is over some region of space you can
find the coordinate transformation which
will straighten out the metric but not
everywhere
so you know a space can be locally flat
so it can be
flat in some region
but that doesn't mean it's black
oh it can always be flattened
in a
in a vicinity in a differential
infinitesimally small vicinity of a
point yes that's right but uh that that
that of course is true
but i mean sometimes it can happen that
the space might even be flat over some
extended region
for example just take this table put a
put a lump in it a bump in
it over here and
the lump comes up and goes over like
that it has some regions of negative
curvature and positive curvature and
those curvatures cannot be gotten rid of
but still over here you could still
fix up the metric so that it looks flat
all right that's the basic idea of a
metric tensor and it is
the key
thing the key object of ramanian
geometry the subject we're doing is
romanian geometry yeah do you have a
space that's flat except for one point
yes yes you can
yes that's right the tip of a cone
that's right a cone is a space which
cannot be flattened but you can flatten
out any patch of it all right so here's
our cone that's a good point
here's our cone
and if i slice the cone like that and
open it up
i make a
thing which looks like this it can be
flattened onto the blackboard and then
if i take my coordinates in the
blackboard to be good old cartesian
coordinates that lays out some
coordinates on here which are flat
but
it's always going to fail at the tip so
yes so the tip of the cone is an
obstruction to finding global
uh flat coordinates i use the term flat
coordinates which is an abusive
terminology
flat coordinates i mean coordinates with
this property
all right let's um
is this clear
yeah okay let me just do a couple of
examples
of metric tensors of spaces just
the first example
is an example
which is really just flat space
it's flat space and curvy linear
coordinates we've talked about it
abstractly let's do it concretely
a specific example of coordinates that
we use all the time
in which the
in which the lines of constant
coordinate you know the coordinate axes
what we're going to call them
are not straight lines polar coordinates
polar coordinates and two dimensions
polar coordinates in any number of
dimensions but in particular polar
coordinates in two dimensions
are examples of curvy linear coordinates
in a flat space time
a flat space we have not gotten to space
time flat space
all right let's uh just do it
we can work this out easily
so here we have
x and y now i'm talking about two
dimensions
but in these formulas
there's nothing specifically
two-dimensional about it
you may not be able to visualize a
higher dimensional curved space i can't
but
you can push the symbols around and it
doesn't really matter whether m and n go
from one to two or they go from one to
ten
you do exactly the same manipulations
uh
but now i am dealing with a
two-dimensional space that you can
visualize
so there's x and y
and i'm going to replace them by the
polar coordinates r meaning radial
distance and theta meaning angle
so here's a point
and uh it's at a distance r from the
origin
at an angle theta
what we need to know is the relationship
between x and y well x and r and theta
and y and r and theta all right now
that's easy
we just drop a perpendicular here
and
x the x location of this point
is equal to r times cosine of theta
and y is equal to r times sine of theta
cosine of theta
is
adjacent over hypotenuse and sine of
theta is opposite over hypotenuse and
that's what these things say
now i want to write
the metric which we know what it is it's
just the x squared let's write over here
it's the x square plus d y squared
incidentally my use of x and y here is
not for two different coordinate systems
now i should probably call it x1 and x2
to be consistent
but
when i'm dealing with a two-dimensional
blackboard sometimes i will just call it
x and y
and
let's forget this over here the x square
plus the y squared which really i should
call the x1 squared plus the x2 squared
the x squared plus the y squared is
equal to ds squared right
that's good old pythagoras but now all
we have to do in order to rewrite the
metric in terms of r and theta
is to express dx and dy in terms of dr
and d theta so let's do that let's
differentiate this
dx
is equal
to the partial derivative of this with
respect to r
that's cosine theta
times dr
partial of x with respect to r times dr
plus partial of x with respect to theta
what's the partial of x with respect to
theta
that's minus r times sine theta right
when i differentiate cosine i get minus
the sine
so that's minus r times sine theta
okay that's uh that's the x
and what about the y
sorry times d theta
and what about the y same kind of thing
the only difference is now well this
piece is similar
dr sorry
sine of theta
dr
now it's plus r
cosine theta d theta
and now i just want to write the x
squared plus d y squared that's a whole
bunch of terms but they're not very
complicated let's see what we have
when i squared the x squared i'm going
to get things involving d r squared i'm
going to get things involving d theta
squared and i'm going to get things
involving d r times d theta
all right let's look at the d r squared
terms you get one from here cosine
squared times d r squared and you get
one from here which is sine squared d r
squared
when i add them up
cosine squared plus sine squared is one
and so
i'm first of all going to get that this
is equal to
the first contribution will just be dr
squared
that's easy
and it's just gotten by squaring this
term and squaring this term and adding
them together
then there's going to be another term
which comes
with d theta squared
it'll also have this squared plus the
squared
so it's going to have r squared sine
squared theta and it's going to have r
squared cosine squared theta
the minus sign will go away when you
square
so it's just going to be r squared d
theta squared the sine squared plus the
cosine squared again there to one
this is plus r squared d theta squared
and what about the cross term the d r d
theta term let's look at it
from here
squaring this
you'll get a cosine theta sine theta r
with a minus sign
get r cosine theta sine theta with a
minus sign
from this cross term you'll get plus r
cosine theta sine theta and there will
be no cross term
all right so this is the metric
of flat space in polar coordinates
let's write down the components of the
metric
the components of the metric are not now
just zeros and ones
the coefficient here is one but the
coefficient here is more complicated it
depends on position depends on radius
so
first of all what's g r r
i use the index r here to represent the
r coordinate
i'll use g r r and g theta theta instead
of g one and g two instead of one and
two
what's g r
one
why is it one
it's just the coefficient of d r squared
what about g r theta
that's the thing which would multiply d
r times d theta and that's zero there is
none so that's zero so far it looks
exactly the same as flat space but the
new thing comes when i write g theta
theta
and that's not one
it's r squared
so that's the metric of space time sorry
i keep saying space time that's the
metric of two dimensional flat space
in polar coordinates
now if somebody gave you this metric
and you looked at it you say oh this is
kind of complicated the g theta theta
term varies with distance
is this flat space or isn't it flat
space can i find a coordinate
transformation which will straighten it
out so it just becomes the x square plus
the y squared well in this case of
course we know the answer is yes
and it's just this coordinate
transformation
if i go from off if i gave you this
metric
this set of components
and i
undid
in other words i go in the opposite
direction
and work out the metric in terms of x
and y i find that it's the x square plus
d y squared
so that is a flat space
by definition
there are a set of coordinates there is
a set of coordinates
uh
more than one of course you can tilt the
coordinates and rotate them and
translate them into all kinds of things
but there's at least one coordinate
system
where the metric just looks like the
kronecker delta
so that's flat despite the fact that in
this form
things have a non-linear complicated
dependence on on the radial distance
yeah does the off diagonal term being
zero tell you anything about it yes it
doesn't tell you anything about the
space in this case it tells you
something about the choice of
coordinates i'll tell you no good i i
meant to come to that right now let me
tell you exactly what it tells you
it tells you
all right let's
yeah
let's look at the lines of constant r
and the lines of constant theta the
lines of constant r are circles
the lines of constant theta are straight
lines from the origin
the fact that there's no cross term is
an indication that the lines of constant
r and the lines of constant theta are
perpendicular to each other
that's also of course true to the lines
of constant x and y
they're perpendicular to each other
uh
but that's that's the meaning of the
cross term vanishing
that the r and theta or that the axes
the lines of constant coordinate or you
can think of them as the axes are
perpendicular to each other that i have
not changed by doing polar coordinates i
could have used some more complicated
coordinates for example ones which look
like this
that's an interesting exercise find some
coordinates look which uh which helps
where these lines are not perpendicular
and then you would have had a g r theta
okay so the uh
so there was nothing particularly
special about the fact that this
vanished other than my particular choice
of
metric happen to have this
perpendicularity
aspect to it
all right let me uh give you
the metric for a sphere
and i will allow you
to prove
that you cannot straighten out the
sphere that you cannot find coordinates
in which the sphere is flat
this is a unit sphere of radius one
that doesn't matter very much that's got
nothing to do with it i'll just i've
just chosen the sphere to have radius
one
all right so here are my coordinates
now i could use many different sets of
coordinates on the sphere it doesn't
matter which set of coordinates i use
i won't be able to straighten out the uh
the coordinate system but i'm going to
give you one set and the one set
is basically a good old longitudinal
latitude except i always measure
longitude from the south pole
in other words uh no i measure latitude
from the latitude latitude from the
south pole right longitudinally it goes
east west right this is another thing i
can never remember
longitude is east west latitude is north
south
and just because i'm used to it i always
choose
the latitude yes the latitude to be zero
at the south pole
all right so
you pick a point on the sphere
it doesn't have to be on the great
doesn't have to be on the great circle
and you locate it
by
a polar angle a polar angle is one word
for it or latitude
which i'll call phi
and also a longitude which i'll call
theta
those are two coordinates good set of
coordinates for um
for a sphere
the lines of constant theta and the
lines of constant phi are perpendicular
so i still have a case with a
where i'm not going to have a cross term
and now you can take any
small vector or any small interval
the small interval is characterized by a
d theta and d phi
and you can write down
the distance from one point to another
using pythagoras theorem on the sphere
and i'll write down the answer for you
it's just d phi squared
it's as i said this is radius r equal
one
it's defy squared plus
sine of theta sine sine of
phi
square sine of phi squared
d theta squared
you